window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Digital_Logic - Number_System — Slot 3 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Number_System — Slot 3",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Let X be the number of distinct 16-bit integers in 2's complement representation. Let Y be the number of distinct 16 bit integers in sign magnitude representation. Then X-Y is ________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "1",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39546/gate2016-2-9#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>The 16 bit 2's complement representation of an integer is 1111 1111 1111 0101;   its decimal representation is__________ . <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "-11",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39649/gate2016-1-7#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>The decimal number has 64 digits. The number of bits needed for its equivalent binary representation is? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2015)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>200</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>213</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>246</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>277</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>213</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/50363/isro2015-78\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>The number of 1's in the binary representation of \\((3*4096 + 15*256 + 5*16 + 3)\\) are: <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2015)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>8</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>9</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>10</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>12</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>10</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2624/gate1995-2-12-isro2015-9\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>The code which uses 7 bits to represent a character is : <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2015)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>ASCII</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>BCD</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>EBCDIC</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Gray</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>ASCII</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/46690/isro2015-6\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>The range of integers that can be represented by an n bit 2's complement number system is: <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2015)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(-2^{n-1} \\text { to }\\left(2^{n-1}-1\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(-\\left(2^{n-1}-1\\right) \\text { to }\\left(2^{n-1}-1\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(-2^{n-1} \\text { to } 2^{n-1}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(-\\left(2^{n-1}+1\\right) \\text { to }\\left(2^{n-1}-1\\right)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(-2^{n-1} \\text { to }\\left(2^{n-1}-1\\right)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1352/gate2005-16-isro2009-18-isro2015-2\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Which of the given number has its IEEE-754 32-bit floating point representation as (0 10000000 110 0000 0000 0000 0000 0000) <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2015)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>2.5</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>3.5</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>4.5</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>3.5</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/50581/isro2015-1\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Consider the equation \\((43)_{x}=(y3)_{8}\\) where x and y are unknown. The number of possible solutions is ______________ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "5",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8494/gate2015-3-49#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>How many different BCD numbers can be stored in 12 switches ? (Assume two position or on-off switches). <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2014)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(2^{12}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(2^{12}-1\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(10^{12}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(10^{3}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(10^{3}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/50455/isro2014-27\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>In the standard IEEE 754 single precision floating point representation, there is 1 bit for sign, 23 bits for fraction and 8 bits for exponent. What is the precision in terms of the number of decimal digits? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2014)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>5</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>6</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>7</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>8</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>7</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/15030/isro2014-8\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>The value of a float type variable is represented using the single-precision 32-bit floating\npoint format of IEEE-754 standard that uses 1 bit for sign, 8 bits for biased exponent and 23\nbits for mantissa. A float type variable x is assigned the decimal value of -14.25. The\nrepresentation of x in hexadecimal notation is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>C1640000H</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>416C0000H</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>41640000H</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>C16C0000H</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>C1640000H</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2011/gate2014-2-45#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Consider the equation \\((123)_{5}=(x8)_{y}\\)  with x and y as unknown. The number of possible\nsolutions is _____ . <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "3",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1961/gate2014-2-8#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>The base (or radix) of the number system such that the following equation holds is_______. <br> \\(\\frac{312}{20}=13.1\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "5",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1766/gate2014-1-8#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>The binary equivalent of the decimal number 42.75 is <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>101010 . 110</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>100110 . 101</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>101010 . 101</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>100110 . 110</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>101010 . 110</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/45672/isro-2013-77\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Two eight bit bytes 11000011 and 01001100 are added. What are the values of the overflow, carry and zero flags respectively, if the arithmetic unit of the CPU uses 2's complement form? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0,1,1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1,1,0</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1,0,1</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>0,1,0</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>0,1,0</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/43814/isro-2013-17\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
